A Guide to the Papers of Mark Twain, 1862-1946
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Mark Twain 1862-1946, bulk 1872-1910
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6314, etc.
This collection consists of approximately 1500 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift and purchase.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains manuscripts, personal correspondence, business correspondence and documents, illustrations, paintings and photographs.
The manuscripts include The Jumping Frog. In English. Then in French. Then clawed back into a civilized language once more by patient, unremunerated toil, six chapters of A tramp abroad, one chapter of The gilded age, prefaces to the English editions of The innocents abroad and Roughing it, and several other shorter pieces together with Susy Clemens's Biography of Mark Twain with his footnotes.
Family correspondence consists of cheerful letters to his wife Olivia Clemens and daughters Susy, Clara and Jean about his travels, lecture audiences, and acquaintances. There are also letters to his mother Jane L. Clemens, his brother Orion and family, his nephew Sam Moffett and his sister-in-law and her husband Susan Langdon and Theodore Crane.
Business correspondence concerns Twain's emergence from the bankruptcy of Charles L. Webster Publishing Co. in which he was the majority stockholder. There are also book contracts, papers concerning his ill fated Paige typesetter investment, and papers concerning Edward H. House's unsuccessful suit against him over dramatization rights to The prince and the pauper.
There is professional correspondence with authors, editors, and publishers in the United States and England including Hjalmar Boyesen, George Washington Cable, William Dean Howells, Albert Bigelow Paine, George Bernard Shaw, and Charles Dudley Warner.
Other correspondents include fellow journalists and miners in the U.S. West in the 1860s, voyagers on "The Quaker City," friends in Hartford, Ct., Hannibal, Mo., and Keokuk, Ia., members of the Players Club and other societies to which he belonged, friends from his travels, and his reading public.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series: Series I: Manuscripts; Series II: Letters; Series III: Documents; Series IV: Photographs, Images, and Illustrations; Series V: Miscellaneous; and, Series VI: Charles L. Webster & Company Debt Receipts
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - "Ah Sin" by Mark Twain and Bret Harte, with printed prompt book. [187?], AMs
  - "At the Shrine of Saint Wagner" [1891 August], AMsS, 40 p.
    Travel sketch of Mark Twain's visit to the Bayreuth Opera Festival; with author's corrections.
  - Autobiography 1906-1907, Proof Sheets
    Proof sheets with author's corrections, notes, and instructions for serial publication in the North American Review.
  - Autobiographical Sketch, [1899 March 31]; AMs, 4 p. (Box 1)
    Note at top of page one requests recipient asks Samuel E. Moffett to write autobiographical sketch and says Olivia L. Clemens will look over it before it is published. S.L.C.
  - "Be Good. Be Good", [1907?] November 14; AMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Poem; "To Margaret." M.T.
  - Biography of Mark Twain by Susy Clemens 1885-1886 July 4, AMsS, 131 p., brown leather lined notebook
    Account of Mark Twain's life, includes copies of letters, 1884 December 14 -1885 July 26, to Susy from Mark Twain discussing family activities, Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, anecdotes from his travels, and suggestion to read Morte d'Arthur, with two letters in German; copy of Mark Twain's comments on Ulysses S. Grant, comparing Grant to Lancelot; copy of Mark Twain's account of Susy Clemens ' visit to Grant; copy of letter, 1885 July 27, from Mark Twain to Editor of The Sun on Grant's funeral; copy of letter 1885 April 16 from Susan Langdon Crane to Olivia L. Clemens concerning their father Jervis Langdon's death and a comparison to reports of Grant's last day; copy of letter, 1884 January 21, George Washington Cable to Mark Twain thanking Twain for invitation; copy of a letter fragment, 1886 May 3, from unknown correspondent in Stonington, CT, with comment from Mark Twain that Susy must have lost rest of letter; copy of letter, n.d., from unknown correspondent from the Valley of Virginia concerning correspondent's enjoyment of Innocents Abroad; several stories by Susy; copy of Mark Twain's Lady Jane Grey scene for family production of The Prince and the Pauper; copy of newspaper article reporting comments of James Redpath on Mark Twain and his publication of Grant's memoirs; clipping of article on Mark Twain's home by George Parsons Lathrop; clippings of comments on Twain's 50th birthday by Joel Chandler Harris, Frank R. Stockton, and Charles Dudley Warner, with clipping of poem by Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr., "To Mark Twain on his 50th birthday"; clipping, 1886 January 30, on Mark Twain's appearance before U.S. Senate Committee on Patents. With notes by Mark Twain.
  - Biography of Mark Twain; footnotes by Mark Twain n.d., AMs, 32 p.
    Supplementary information and suggested changes; descriptions of the play of The Prince and the Pauper and the home productions of the Clemens and neighboring children; description of Susy Clemens ' moral courage and character.
  - "The Cat", n.d.; AMS, 1 p.; with proof (signed S.L.C.) and clipping. (Box 1)
    Photo caption for one of Mark Twain's pictures accompanying article Three Famous Humorists Out of Doors.
  - Clemens Family Travel Journal, 1895-1896; AMsS; black bound volume with gilt trim.
    Includes copies of four letters, 1895 November 3 -1896 February 17, of Olivia L. Clemens to Jean Clemens and Susan Langdon Crane and of two letters, 1896 January 13 and 1896 February 18, of Clara Clemens to family members concerning their travels with Mark Twain in India, Australia, New Zealand, etc., new and old friends, family activities, and Mark Twain's lectures; with notes on artists, engravings of historic heroines, and a number of blank pages.
  - "Colonel Sellars as Scientist" by Mark Twain and William Dean Howellsn.d., AMsS
  - "Concerning the Jews" [1898?], AMsS, 37 p.
    Article denouncing anti-semitism; with author's corrections; includes ALS 1898 March 14 Grant I. Rosenzweig, Kansas City, MO, to Mark Twain.
  - "The Death Disk", [1901]; AMs, 42 p.; bound in red leather.
    With author's corrections and notes and signed engraved picture of Mark Twain.
  - "The Earth Invoketh the Sun", 1892 November 27; AMsS, 1 p., with envelope (Box 1)
    Poem inscribed "To Livy, November. 27, 1892."
  - "From the London Times of 1904" [ca.1898], AMsS, 35 p.
    With author's corrections.
  - The Gilded Age; Ch. VII, "Colonel Sellers at Home", [ca.1873]; AMs, 23 p.; bound in blue leather
    In Mark Twain's hand with author's corrections; numbered pages 175 to 200 1/2, lacking pages 177 and 184; w/printed Ch. VII from original 1873 edition, a special printed title page, and a reproduction photograph of Mark Twain.
  - The Gilded Age; fragments, [ca.1873]; AMs, 12 p. (Box 1)
    Non-continuous fragments; nine pages in Mark Twain's hand; three in Charles Dudley Warner's.
  - The Gilded Age; fragment, [ca. February 1873]; AMsS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Fragment by Mark Twain; marked page 27; re a perpetual-motion machine.
  - "The Great Revolution in Pitcairn" [ca.1879], AMsS, 65 p.
    With author's corrections; page 10 has three pinned newspaper clippings for inclusion in printed text.
  - "How the Chimney Sweep Got the Ear of the Emperor" [1901], AMsS, 26 p.
  - "A Humorist to the Rescue" by Richard Watson Gilder, [ca. 1899]; AMs, 3 p. (Box 1)
    Re Mark Twain.
  - The Innocents Abroad; "Preface to the English Edition", 1872 July; AMsS, 2 p. (Box 1)
    With author's corrections; written for use in George Routledge and Sons edition of The Innocents Abroad; with AN signed S.L.C., Twain requests publisher "to tear up the other and use this one."
  - The Innocents Abroad; Preface "To the English Reader", 1872 July; AMsS, 4 p. (Box 1)
    With author's corrections; written for use in George Routledge and Sons edition of The Innocents Abroad.
  - "The Invalid's Story / The Limburger Cheese Story" n.d., AMsS, 26 p.
    With author's corrections, engraved picture of Mark Twain, a special printed title page, and ALS 1909 December 3 Luther S. Livingston to J. R. Clemens.
  - " John T. Lewis ", n.d.; AMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Photo caption for one of Mark Twain's pictures accompanying article "Three Famous Humorists Out of Doors."
  - "The Jumping Frog. In English. Then in French. Then clawed back into a civilized language once more by patient, unremunerated toil" 1873 June 30, AMsS, 40 p.
    With author's corrections and ALS [1873] July 7 Mark Twain to [Elisha] Bliss; at bottom of manuscript, "London, June 30, 1873" crossed out and replaced with "Hartford, March 1875."
  - "Manners", n.d.; AMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
    Re American manners.
  - Notes in margins of printed article "Conditions in the Congo State: Report of King Leopold's Commission", [ca. 1905 November]; AMs, 7 p. (Box 1)
    Criticism of printed article. With ANS [ca. 1905] Mark Twain to [Robert] Bacon re article.
  - Notes on Thomas Carlyle, [ca.1881 February]; AMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
    Brief lines with some rewrites on thoughts of Carlyle and his perceived dislike of Americans.
  - "The Paradise of the Rheumatics"[1891], AMsS, 41 p.; bound in red leather
    With author's corrections, hand-lettered title page, and reproduced photograph of Mark Twain.
  - "Party Cries in Ireland", AMs, 7 p. (Box 1)
    (pages 1 and 7 are glued onto backing sheets)
  - "Passengers to Captain Mouland" 1872 November 23, AMsS, 4 p.
    Signed by 23 passengers including Mark Twain; with ALS [1872] December 3 Mark Twain to Captain [John E.] Mouland and ALS [1873] January 22 Mark Twain to Captain [John E.] Mouland.
  - The Personal Recollections of Joan of Arc fragment, [ante 1896]; AMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
    Fragment; marked p.282 and titled Taxes on top of one page.
  - "Plasmon" Food Stock, [1903]; TMs, 15 p. (Box 1)
    Account concerning Mark Twain's involvement with Plasmon and a stock swindle perpetrated on him by men in the company. Pencilled across the right corner of the manuscript is "a food stock swindle."
  - "Play Acting" fragment, n.y. August 11; AMs, 2 p.; in ALS [n.y.] August 11, Mark Twain to Unknown)
    Fragment. Requests sentence beginning "And still another panic of fright" be added to article.
  - Press release written on Clara Clemens' wedding to Ossip Gabrilowitsch, [1909 October 5]; TMs, 3 p. (Box 1)
    Re the wedding, the guests, Mark Twain's library, and his current activities. With corrections in unknown hand.
  - A Record of the Small Foolishness of Susie and "Bay" Clemens (Infants) 1876 August-1885 June 7, AMsS, 113 p., bound volume
    Account of Susie, Clara ("Bay"), and later Jean Clemens ' sayings and activities, with Mark Twain's observations.
  - "Report of my death was an exaggeration", 1897 May 31; AMsS, 7 p. (Box 1)
    Re concerning origins of the premature report of Mark Twain's death. M.T. With three newspaper clippings concerning the story surrounding this report.
  - "The Regular Toast. Woman -- God Bless Her" [1891 May], AMsS, 16 p.
    With author's corrections; text of speech given in 1882; signed " Mark Twain, Samuel Langhorne Clemens. Hartford, May 1891."
  - Roughing It; "Preface to the English Edition", [1872]; AMsS, 3 p. (Box 1)
    Written for use in George Routledge and Sons [1872] edition of Roughing It; with corrections and deletions in Twain's hand. M.T.
  - Roughing It; "Preface to the English E[dition]", [1872]; AMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Copy of Mark Twain's proposed preface (see above) but in another's hand, with annotation by Twain.
  - Roughing It; proof corrections for "old edition", n.d.; AMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
    In Mark Twain's hand.
  - Roughing It; "To the Late Cain", [1871] May 15; AMsS, 7 p. (Box 1)
    Dedication for Roughing It enclosed in ALS [1871] May 5 Mark Twain to "Friend Bliss" ( Elisha Bliss ).
  - Roughing It; notes on illustrations, n.d.; AMs, 2 p. (Box 1)
    Notes in unidentified hand about illustrations for Roughing It with annotations on pagination.
  - Roughing It; Horace Greeley letter, n.d.; Proof (Box 1)
  - "She Pondered Long the Question", AMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Poem
  - Speech on Edwin Booth with "The Long Clam" speech, n.d.; AMs, 7 p. (Box 1)
    Remarks on Edwin Booth followed by "The Long Clam" speech.
  - Speech to Girard College [1889], AMsS, 11 p.
    Argues against the teaching of religion at Girard College, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
  - Speech to New York Press Club, [1869 June 1]; AMsS, 9 p. (Box 1)
    Discusses "The Reliable Contraband" as a source of news in the Civil War.
  - "Three Famous Authors Out of Doors", n.d.; TMsS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Photo captions for "Mark Twain at Quarry Hill Farm"; "Even Mark Twain Nods"; "Mark Twain and an Old Family Friend" (John T. Lewis); "Mark Twain and his Porcelain Cat"; with ANS, "O.K. S. L. Clemens."
  - "To Mrs. Ditson", 1902 February 5; AMS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Quotation on music; with manuscript bar of music. M.T.
  - A Tramp Abroad; Ch. 14 "To Heidelberg on a Raft" [1879], AMs, 24 p.; bound in red leather
    With author's corrections, picture of Mark Twain's sculpture bust, a special printed title page, and printed chapter 14 from first edition of A Tramp Abroad.
  - A Tramp Abroad; Ch. 25 (part), Ch. 26, 27, [1879]; AMs, 149 p.; bound in green leather
    With author's corrections, reproduction photograph of Mark Twain with printed autograph. ()
  - A Tramp Abroad; Ch. 31 "From Lucerne to Interlaken" [1879], AMs, 48 p.; bound in red leather
    With author's corrections, engraving of Mark Twain with printed autograph, special printed title page, and printed chapter 31 from first edition of A Tramp Abroad.
  - A Tramp Abroad; Ch. 35, fragments, 1879; AMs, 4 p. (Box 1)
    Non-continuous fragments from chapter 35 of A Tramp Abroad.
  - A Tramp Abroad; Ch. 37, fragments, [1879]; AMs, 7 p. (Box 1)
    Non-continuous fragments from chapter 37 of A Tramp Abroad.
  - A Tramp Abroad; Ch. 39, [1879]; AMs, 34 p.; bound in red leather
    With author's corrections, reproduction photograph of Mark Twain with printed autograph, and hand-lettered title page.
  - A Tramp Abroad; Ch.45 "A Catastrophe Which Cost Eleven Lives", [1879]; AMs, 9 p.; bound in blue leather
  - "A True Story" by Mark Twain [1874], AMsS, 29 p.
    With author's corrections; bottom of manuscript p. 28 torn off.
  - "Yes I have tried a number of summer homes" [1905] October 9, AMs, 9 p.
    With author's corrections and ALS 1905 October [12] Sunday Mark Twain to Frederick A. Duneka.
  - "Lines written in the Greeting Book of the Mark Twain Society" by James Galsworthy 1930 September 2, AMsS, 1 p.
    Verse to Mark Twain; copy in James Galsworthy's hand.
- Series II: Letters
  - William Elgin, Hannibal, MO, to George Rust, Baltimore, MD, 1844 January 13; ALS, 2 p. (Box 1)
    Discusses his activities, family news, and life in Hannibal, MO.
  - Mark Twain, Carson City, [Nevada Territory], to William H. Clagett, 1862 February 28; ALS, 6 p., with envelope and two postscripts attached; bound in blue leather with typescript copy of letter lacking first two pages.
    Has received letter and mining deeds; describes character of his recently deceased dog; mentions Clagett's wife, other friends, his activities, and family news; reports on war in Missouri and the taking of Forts Henry and Donelson; refers to characters from [Dicken's] Dombey and Son. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Carson City, [Nevada Territory], to William H. Clagett, 1862 March 8; ALS, 4 p., with envelope; bound in blue volume with typescript copy of letter.
    Is sending office supplies; mentions friends and family; discusses his attempt to steal a dog; says that he is writing because he likes to, although he has no news; says he is leaving for Esmeralda if "nothing happens"; complains about minister; adds that they have not heard from home. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Esmeralda, [Nevada Territory], to William H. Clagett, 1862 April 18; ALS, 2 p., with envelope; bound in blue volume with typescript copy of letter.
    Describes mining and claims in Esmeralda and his purchase of mining claims; is discouraged; discusses opportunity to learn secret process to get more ore out of the mines; encourages Clagett not to sell out. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Esmeralda, Nevada Territory, to Orion Clemens, Carson City, Nevada Territory, 1862 June 22; ALS, 4 p., with envelope. (Box 1)
    Discusses mining and mining claims; encloses sketch of mine locations; plans to leave soon if they do not strike something; says since 1853 has rarely been in one place more than six months; complains about the printers for the [Territorial] Enterprise who are meddling with his punctuation; mentions business letters of Barstow and cautions Orion not to tell 'Gillesp' about them; suggests keeping Josh's letters in scrapbook; has quit writing for The Gate. Sam.
  - Mark Twain, Esmeralda, [Nevada Territory], to William H. Clagett, 1862 September 9; ALS, 2 p., with envelope; bound in blue volume with typescript copy of letter.
    Congratulates him on being elected representative; hopes he will be elected Senator when Nevada becomes a state; is angry with course of war and Union retreat and unhappy with talk of strategy that accomplishes nothing; discusses mutual friends and mining matters; disgusted with climate and may move to Colorado mines; encloses power of attorney. S.L.C.
  - Orion Clemens, Heaton's Station, CA, to Jane Lampton Clemens and Pamela Clemens Moffett, St. Louis, MO, 1866 March 19-20; ALS, 13 p., with envelope. (Box 1)
    Describes his travels in California, mines, snowfall, travel by stage and sleighs, the Donner Party tragedy, and people and places in Nevada County.
  - Mark Twain, Virginia City, Nevada, to Robert M. Howland, [1866] October 29; ALS (photocopy), 1 p. (Box 1)
    Talks about his lectures in Virginia City, Gold Hill, Silver City and Carson; suggests Howland ask Abe Curry about audience turnout; says he had looked for Curry in Sacramento but missed him. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, St. Louis, MO, to Charles H. Webb, [1867] March 19; ALS, 2 p. (Box 1)
    Everything going well with the pilots and New Orleans river men; asks when book ( The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County ) is expected to be published; plans to lecture if book not published soon. Mark.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, New York, to "Dear Folks" [ Jane Lampton Clemens et al.], [1867] April 15; ALS, 2 p. (Box 1)
    Discusses his signing onto the Holy Land excursion on the "Quaker City"; says his book ( The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County ) should be out in two weeks and plans to lecture after that; since he left [ California] his friends have signed two hundred subscribers for the book; asks to be remembered to various friends; will write to Annie [Moffett Webster] and Katie Lampton. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, New York, to Frank Fuller, 1867 June 7; ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Authorizes Fuller to collect all money from The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County; gives his mother's address in St. Louis. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, on board "Quaker City", to [Peter] Kinney, [1867 ante August 26] Sunday; ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Asks him to print enclosed draft (not present) and send him a proof; is enclosing statistics (not present) for Kinney's use if wanted. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Washington, DC, to Mary Mason Fairbanks, [1867] December 2; ALS, 6 p. (Box 1)
    Mentions difficulties in meeting her and Charlie [Langdon]; discusses at length his differences with the "Quaker City" passengers; finding keeping promises not to publish anything unpleasant about the Quaker City passengers troublesome; unable to promise not to swear and discusses swearing at length; mentions his true friends on the "Quaker City"; has received several book offers because of letters published in The Tribune; likes offer from American Publishing Company; reports Albert D. Richardson's success with the company; notes for whom he is engaged as correspondent and is unable to accept lecturing invitations. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Washington, DC, to Charles H. Webb, [1868?] January 15; ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Thanks for books; "tackled the Stag" who swore all the charges were false; wishes Webb were there. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, San Francisco, CA, to Elisha Bliss, 1868 May 28; ALS, 2 p. (Box 1)
    Relates that H. H. Bancroft is anxious to have agency for his book on the west coast, Japan and China; comments on sales of Albert D. Richardson's Beyond the Mississippi and company canvassers; has friends in Japan and China and was urged not to forget them; expects to be finished with manuscript in twenty days and will go east then. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, New York, to Joseph H. Twichell, 1868 November 28; ALS, 3 p. (Box 1)
    Announces with joy his conditional engagement with Olivia Langdon; describes his request for permission from her parents, conditions to be met for the engagement, and Olivia's acceptance of his proposal. M.T.
  - Olivia Lewis Langdon to Mary Mason Fairbanks, 1868 December 1; ALS, 8 p. (Box 1)
    Mentions Fairbanks's 'Holy Land' letters; requests her appraisal of Mark Twain, especially if she thinks the reformation of his character is permanent; recognizes Twain's genius but concern for her daughter prompts her to inquire; discusses news and health of family.
  - Mark Twain to Silas A. Packard, [1869 June 1]; ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Unable to come but sends letter to be read and speech for a meeting; if proceedings are published would like copies for his scrap-book; is "pleasantly employed"; insists punctuation and text are exactly as he wants them.
  - Mark Twain, Buffalo, NY, to Elisha Bliss, 1869 August 12; TL (copy), 1 p. (Box 1)
    Broke off negotiations with Cleveland Herald and bought third interest in The Buffalo Express; will give up lecturing until next year; praises look of book ( The Innocents Abroad ); requests copies to be sent to various people and newspapers; will send Elmira reviews and a copy of a flattering letter. Typed signature S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Buffalo, NY, to Henry M. Crane, 1869 August 21; ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Unable to lecture because he is working for a newspaper and will be married soon; hopes and expects to be excused from New England lecture contract; unable to lecture at Kingston either. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Buffalo, NY, to Henry M. Crane, Rondout, NY, 1869 September 8; ALS, 4 p. (Box 1)
    Has replied to Abby that he will not lecture in either town; because of this reply, can not agree to lecture in Rondout; has refused other lecture and wishes to clear up confusion over other engagements; has postponed wedding until February because of his lecture engagements; discusses his desire to be out of lecturing and support family with newspaper. S.L.C. and M.T.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Buffalo, NY, to Henry M. Crane, 1869 September 21; ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Re lecture engagements; forwarding letter to his Boston agent, who is straightening out matters with Medbury. S.L.C.
  - Plymouth Young People's Association lecture committee to Mark Twain; overwritten with ALS [1869] Mark Twain to James Redpath with additional sheet., 1869 December 6; ALS, 4 p. (Box 1)
    Extends lecture invitation. On recto, verso and additional sheet, ALS [1869] Mark Twain to James Redpath says he discussed above invitation with Horatio C. King, a committee member; does not wish to lecture outside New England again, especially not in Brooklyn; complains about Miss Watson and the arrangements she made for a misrepresented Brooklyn lecture; discusses arrangements to solve the problem. M.T.